A Finding Aid to the Irving Blum Gallery and Ferus Gallery Announcements, 1961-1973, in the Archives of American Art
Archives of American Art
Irving Blum Gallery and Ferus Gallery announcements
1961-1972
Archives of American Art
Irving Blum Gallery
AAA.irviblum
Archival Resource Key
0.2 Linear feet
The Irving Blum Gallery and Ferus Gallery announcements consist of 32 announcements for exhibitions at the Los Angeles Ferus Gallery (1957-1966) and its successor the Irving Blum Gallery (1966-circa 1972). Exhibition announcements are for many exhibitions of southern California contemporary and pop artists, as well as New York artists. Artists represented by announcements include John Altoon, Don Bachardy, Larry Bell, Billy Al Bengston, Robert Irwin, Jasper Johns, Donald Judd, Craig Kauffman, Roy Lichtenstein, Edward Moses, Kenneth Noland, Ad Reinhardt, Ed Ruscha, Frank Stella, and Andy Warhol, among others.
Provenance
Mrs. Rochella Orchard donated the Ferus Gallery and Irving Blum Gallery announcements on February 22, 1979.
Alternative Forms Available
This site provides access to the records of Irving Blum Gallery (Los Angeles, Calif.) in the Archives of American Art that were digitized in 2009. The records have been scanned in their entirety, and total 32 images.
Related Material
Also found at the Archives of American Art is an oral history interview with Irving Blum conducted by Paul Cummings on May 31-June 23, 1977.
Restrictions on Access
The collection has been digitized and is available online via AAA's website.
Historical Note
In 1957, Walter Hopps (1932-2005) and Edward Kienholz (1927-1994) opened the contemporary art Ferus Gallery on North La Cienega Boulevard in Los Angeles, California. Kienholz sold his share to Irving Blum (b. 1930) one year later. Hopps left in 1962 to become curator and, later, director of the Pasadena Art Museum. Ferus Gallery closed in 1966 and Irving Blum maintained sole ownership and changed the gallery's name to Irving Blum Gallery.
Ferus Gallery was the first gallery in the Los Angeles area to show contemporary American art, and focused heavily on contemporary Southern California artists, such as John Altoon, Larry Bell, Billy Al Bengston, Wallace Berman, Robert Irwin, Craig Kauffman, Ed Kienholz, Ed Moses, Richard Ruben, among many others. Likewise, Ferus Gallery helped to solidify the reputations of many established New York artists, including Roy Lichtenstein, Jasper Johns, Frank Stella, Richard Diebenkorn, Andy Warhol, and others.
The inaugural exhibition at the Ferus Gallery was "Objects on the New Landscape Demanding of the Eye" (March 15 - April 11, 1957), a group show including the work of Frank Lobdell, Jay DeFeo, Craig Kauffman, Richard Diebenkorn, John Altoon and Clyfford Still. Los Angeles artists who had their first solo shows at the gallery included: Wallace Berman (1957), Billy Al Bengston (1958), Ed Moses (1958), Robert Irwin (1959), John Mason (1959), Kenneth Price (1960), Llyn Foulkes (1962), Larry Bell (1962) and Ed Ruscha (1963).
In 1957 the gallery was temporarily closed after LAPD officers arrested and charged Wallace Berman with obscenity over work in his exhibition. It was his first and last solo show.
In 1962 "Andy Warhol: Campbell's Soup Cans" was Andy Warhol's first solo pop art exhibition and the first exhibition of the Soup Cans. Five of the canvases sold for $100 each, but Blum bought them back to keep the set intact.
Irving Blum designed many of the exhibition announcements for the gallery with a graphic aesthetic.
In 2007, "The Cool School" was released, a documentary film about the Ferus Gallery and its eccentric artists.
Scope and Content Note
The Irving Blum Gallery and Ferus Gallery announcements consist of 32 announcements for exhibitions at the Los Angeles Ferus Gallery (1957-1966) and its successor the Irving Blum Gallery (1966-circa 1972). Exhibition announcements are for many exhibitions of southern California contemporary and pop artists, as well as New York artists. Artists represented by announcements include John Altoon, Don Bachardy, Larry Bell, Billy Al Bengston, Robert Irwin, Jasper Johns, Donald Judd, Craig Kauffman, Roy Lichtenstein, Edward Moses, Kenneth Noland, Ad Reinhardt, Ed Ruscha, Frank Stella, and Andy Warhol, among others.
Although these announcements are scattered, they provide insight to and documentation of the southern California LA art scene and the Beat era. The exhibition announcements themselves are quite unique.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged as 2 series:
Missing Title
Series 1: Ferus Gallery Announcements, 1961-1965 (Box 1; 20 folders)
Series 2: Irving Blum Gallery Announcements, 1969-1972 (Box 1; 12 folders)
Art galleries, Commercial -- California; Johns, Jasper, 1930-; Ruscha, Edward; Stella, Frank; Warhol, Andy, 1928-; Kauffman, Craig, 1932-2010; Moses, Ed, 1926-; Noland, Kenneth, 1924-; Judd, Donald, 1928-; Irwin, Robert, 1928-; Ferus Gallery (Los Angeles, Calif.); Bengston, Billy Al; Lichtenstein, Roy, 1923-1997; Reinhardt, Ad, 1913-1967; Bell, Larry, 1939-; Bachardy, Don, 1934-; Altoon, John, 1925-
- Ferus Gallery Announcements, 1961-1965; Series 1; Archival Resource Key; 20 Folders Box 1
  Scope and Contents note
  Exhibition announcements for Ferus Gallery arranged in chronological order. Exhibition announcements for Ferus Gallery arranged in chronological order.
  - John Altoon and Richard Ruben, 1961 September 18; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Robert Irwin, 1962 May 8; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - John Altoon, 1962 October 15; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Billy Al Bengston, 1962 November 12; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Joseph Cornell, 1962 December 10; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Frank Stella, 1963 February 18; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Roy Lichtenstein, 1963 April 1; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Edward Moses, 1963 April 29; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Altoon, Bell, Bengston, Defoe, Irwin, Kauffman, Lobdell, Mason, Moses, Price, Ruben, Ruscha, 1963 June 17; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Larry Bell, 1963 November 4; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Kenneth Price, 1964 March 3; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Robert Irwin, 1964 April 7; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Streeter Blair, 1964 May 4; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Josef Albers, 1964 September 15; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Philip Rich, 1965 January 5; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Frank Stella, 1965 January 26; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Larry Bell, 1965 October 26; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Edward Ruscha, 1965 November 16; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Richard Ruben, circa 1961; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Billy Al Bengston, circa 1961; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 20)
- Irving Blum Gallery Announcements, 1969-1972; Series 2; Archival Resource Key; 12 Folders Box 1
  Exhibition announcements for the Irving Blum Gallery arranged in chronological order.
  - Donald Judd, 1969 September 16; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Kelly, Morris, Reinhardt, Stella, Warhol, 1969 December 9; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Don Bachardy, 1970 March 10; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Jasper Johns, 1970 April 21; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Michael Balog, 1970 November 3; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Thirties Style: Paintings, Sculpture, Decorative Images, 1970 December 8; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Richard Diebenkorn, 1971 January 12; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - Frank Stella, 1971 November 9; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - Kenneth Noland, 1971 November 9; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - Tom Holste, 1972 January 18; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - John Duff, 1972 November 14; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - Craig Kauffman, 1972 December 12; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 32)